<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certaine arguments to perswade and prouoke the most honorable and high court of Parliament now assembled and also all other in any high authority, or in any grace, and credite with them that are in high authority, to promote and advance the sincere ministery of the Gospell; as also zealously to speake for the ministers therof now degraded, deprived, silenced, or admonished, or afterward like to be called into question, for subscription, ceremonyes, strict observation of the booke of common prayer, or for other conformitie.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21420</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7736</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117606</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852818</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852818</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18169</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21420)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18169)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 832:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certaine arguments to perswade and prouoke the most honorable and high court of Parliament now assembled and also all other in any high authority, or in any grace, and credite with them that are in high authority, to promote and advance the sincere ministery of the Gospell; as also zealously to speake for the ministers therof now degraded, deprived, silenced, or admonished, or afterward like to be called into question, for subscription, ceremonyes, strict observation of the booke of common prayer, or for other conformitie.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 30, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[W. Jones's secret press]],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Imprinted 1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly also STC 740.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Puritans --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18169:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18169:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CERTAINE ARGVMENTS TO PER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SWADE AND PROVOKE THE MOST <hi>HONORABLE AND HIGH COVRT OF</hi> PAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament now aſſembled, and alſo all other in any high au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, or in any grace, and credite with them that are in <hi>high authoriy, to promote and advance the ſincere Miniſtery of the Goſpell; as alſo zealouſly to ſpeake for the Miniſters therof</hi> now degraded, deprived, ſilenced, or admoniſhed, or afterward like to be called into queſtion, for Subſcription, Ceremonyes, <hi>ſtrict obſervation of the booke of common prayer, or for other conformitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Sam. 2.30.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Them that honor me I will honor: and they that diſpiſe me, shall be deſpiſed.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Math: 12.30</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>He that is not with me, is againſt me: and he that gathereth not with me, ſcattereth.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Therefore,</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1: Cor: 16.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Watch ye: ſtand faſt in the faith; quite you like men, and be ſtrong.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted 1606.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:18169:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18169:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER, Honorable, Worſhipfull. etc.</head>
            <p>TOuching theſe arguments following, my humble petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Chriſtian reader (of whatſoever ſorte and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition) is this, that they may not be taken as procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from one ſuſpecting any religious Noble man or gentleman of the Parliament houſe, but rather from one as with all thanks to God, acknowledging the godly forwardnes of many in both houſes, ſo alſo earneſtly deſiering to quicken the zeale of the beſt, and to provoke all other, to take the cauſe heere handled to heart, not onely as the cauſe of poore diſtreſſed men, but as the cauſe of God; yea, to accompt it alſo the maine cauſe of the whole land, of your ſelues and all your poſteritie, and therefore to prefer the ſame <hi>(according to the daily moſt godly prayer of your ſelues, in your houſe of Parliament)</hi> before all other cauſes whatſoever, either concerning any particuler perſons, or the whole common wealth.</p>
            <p>Whereas I haue perſwaded them to whom I haue directed theſe reaſons to vſe all meanes they may for the doeing of any good; I deſire that my words may not be vncharitably conſtrued of any other <hi>meanes</hi> then ſuch, as are ſutable to the <hi>cauſe,</hi> viz. of good honeſt, lawfull, peaceable &amp; agreable to every mans calling. The like charitable conſtruction I craue of any other wordes, which ſome parhaps may maliciouſly wreſt againſt my ſelf &amp; the cauſe.</p>
            <p>Wheras alſo ſome may ſeeme to pretend feare of his moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Maieſties diſpleaſure to hinder their zeale and courage; ſuch I entreate to conſider, how diſhonorable (if not diſloyall) it is, in good cauſes to feare the diſpleaſure of a Prince, who beſides his
<pb facs="tcp:18169:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>moſt Chriſtian education from his infancy, hath long time publikly given ſo many worthy teſtimonyes of his piety and godlines. <hi>Loue thinketh no evill of any,</hi> much leſſe of ſuch a Chriſtian Prince, <hi>It beleiveth all and hopeth all of every brother,</hi> much more of a religious King. <hi>It is the glory of a King</hi> not only <hi>to find out the ſecrets of other,</hi> but alſo ſometime to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale his owne. Therefore it is not meete by preſent wordes or deedes, (whereof ſometime there may be a deepe reaſon) alwayes to iudge of the mind. <hi>Iehu</hi> pretended one thing (when he procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a ſacrifice for <hi>Baal</hi>) but he intended another: <hi>Ioſeph</hi> a long time delt roughly (both in word and deede) with his brethren; yet in the end he ſheewed himſelfe moſt lovinge and kind vnto them. Our <hi>Saviour</hi> (for the triall of the woman of <hi>Canaan</hi>) ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a long time to repell her ſute, for her daughter, firſt by ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, <hi>2.</hi> by a ſharp reprehenſion of his Diſciples petitioning in her behalfe: and <hi>3.</hi> by a more ſharp anſwer to her ſelfe. At the laſt notwithſtanding, he did moſt graciovſly open the treaſures of his riche compasſion towards her, and ſent her away with a bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant comforte. <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the Father of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> (as <hi>Evſebius</hi> reporteth lib. <hi>1. de vita Conſtantini,</hi> cap. <hi>II.</hi>) at his firſt entrance into the Empire, made ſolemne procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, that all <hi>which ſerved him in his Court, ſhould ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worſhip Devills,</hi> (after the manner of the Heathen) <hi>or giue over their places of dignity and honor, and ſo to be banniſhed from his Court.</hi> But by this meanes when he had tryed them that were faithfull, then (to the farre greater honor of his Princely wiſedome and piety, then if he had plainly and ſimply at the firſt profeſſed the Chriſtian religion,) He diſgraced thoſe that had ſo revolted from God, and rebuked them with a moſt Princely and religious rebuke, ſaying, <hi>That they were Traitors to God, and vnworthy the ſervice of an Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. For how</hi> (quoth he) <hi>can they keepe faith vnviolat to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb facs="tcp:18169:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Emperour, which are manifeſtly convinced to be vnfaithfull to the moſt excellent and mightie God.</hi> On the contrary, thoſe that for conſcience had forſaken their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and given over their honors, he moſt highly graced, <hi>as thoſe that would be faithfull to the Emperour, becauſe they had been ſo vnto God: yea, he pronounced them worthy to be reckoned among the cheife and principall frends of the Emperour, and to be worthily much more eſteemed, than Treaſuries full of great riches.</hi> Therefore alſo he prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſome of them to ſpeciall attendance vpon his owne perſon, and other ſome he advanced to the cheife goverment of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire vnder himſelfe.</p>
            <p>I leaue the application of theſe things. Onely I wiſh ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of them, that men may not be raſhe (vpon any ſuppoſed apparances) to iudge Chriſtian Princes, eſpecially who in fromer times haue many wayes teſtified their ſincere religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yea I wiſh leſſ cenſuring of them, and more earneſt praying for them <hi>in ſecret before him that ſeeth inſecret &amp; hath promiſed to reward openly yea as David bleſed the Lord God of Iſraell, and the counſell of Abigail, and Abigaill her ſelf, for keeping him from ſheading innocent blood, 1</hi> Sam. <hi>25.32.</hi> &amp;tc. ſo (to omit what thanks you may haue from his moſt excellent Maieſty) who alſo knoweth, how euen they, that for the preſent doe moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the matters heerafter pleaded for, will in the end bleſſe God &amp; your counſell, and your ſelues for ſtaying them from their proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their hard courſes againſt the miniſtery of the Goſpell, &amp; the ſalvation of the people depending thervpon?</p>
            <p>Finally, albeit I could haue added many other arguments to theſe that I haue here written for the further wheting of the zeale of thoſe to whom theſe cauſes principally appertayne yet ſeing theſe doe a riſe to ſuch a quantite; I thought it beſt to ſpare the further paynes of my ſelfe, and of the reader: hoping that theſe which I
<pb facs="tcp:18169:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>haue written, ſhall be ſufficient ſo to kindle the zeale of them that loue the Lord Ieſus and his truth, <hi>that they ſhalbe ſo full of matter</hi> (as <hi>Elihu</hi> ſpeaketh of himſelfe <hi>Iob 32.19</hi>) <hi>that their ſpirit within them, ſhall compell them, and that their bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes ſhall be as the wine which hath no vent, and like the new bottles that burſt, that ſo they may ſpeake to take breath, and open their lipps for anſwer of them</hi> (if any ſuch doe ſheew themſelues) that doe oppugne, or ſhall op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne the ſincere miniſtery of the goſpell. In which hope <hi>I commend them to God, and to the word of his Grace.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata</head>
            <p>page 10. lin: 28. repreeſing for represſing page 12. lin: 9 put in, it, at the end page 11 lin: 1 thines for thinges page 13, lin. 19 after ſuckling make a comma ibid: lin: 26 for ſware read ſweare page 14 lin. pen: for agd, read and ibid: lin: vltim: for mounks, read monks page 16 lin: 11 for raa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy read ready page 17 lin: 5 for wouds read words page 19 lin: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> alination for alienation ibid: lin: 19 inmitating for inmitating page 15 lin: 20 for uſe read uſe.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18169:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>CERTAINE ARGVMENTS TO <hi>PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VOKE THIS PRESENT HIGH COVRT</hi> of Parliament to zeale, for the Miniſters <hi>now ſilenced.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>For the ground of all that followeth (to omitt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out long diſcourſe that principall poynt that the Goſpell is the power of God vnto ſalvation (as that which I hope is doubted of none) It is to be conſidered that the Miniſters in perticular aboue mentioned, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> are the Miniſters of Chriſt, ſent by God, and in grace and favor with God. This is euident. 1. by the hatred of all ſortes of the wicked and vngodly men, Papiſts Athiſts &amp; Carnall Goſpellers in ſpeciall manner againſt them. <hi>If ye were of the world</hi> (ſaith our ſavyour) <hi>the world would loue his owne, but becauſe ye are not of the world but I haue choſen you out of the world, therefore the world hateth you. Ioh.</hi> 15.19.2. By their vnbla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eable life in all other things, the matter only of Conformity excepted. This hath bin &amp; dayly is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by thoſe that are Iudges againſt them for the ſaid Conformity. And albeit contempt, ſingularity, and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition be obiected vnto them, yet how vniuſtly this is ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iected, doth evidently appeare by the manifould reproch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es, the great moleſtations, loſſe of liuing, to the vndoing of them ſelues their wiues and Children, and many other wronges, iniuryes, &amp; indignities which they haue ſuffred and dayly doe ſuffer 3. As by their guifts wherwith they are furniſhed for their callinges, and by their paines and dilligence accordingly in their callinges, ſo eſpecially by
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18169:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>the bleſſing of God vpon their ſaid paines and dilligence in the knowledg &amp; obedience of the people in ſuch places where they liue, and in the mutuall loue and peace of ſuch people among them ſelues: wheras in other places men for the moſt parte are ignorant of all duty to God and man, and therefore prophane, irreligious, contentious, and apt to ſedition &amp; rebellion as all experience teacheth vs. This argument iuſtificth their calling. For how could they ſo preach to ſuch effectes of knowledge, godlines, loyalty, peace and loue except they were ſent <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15. That which the Apoſtle ſaith to the Corinthians in the like behalfe touching his Apoſtlſhip, may alſo be ſaid in this touching the miniſtery and calling of theſe men vnto thoſe people where they are and among whom the Lord hath ſo bleſſed their miniſteriall labors, <hi>Are ye not my worke in the Lord? If I be not an Apoſtle to other, yet doubtle I am vnto you: for yea are the ſeale of my Apoſtleſhip in the Lord</hi> 1. <hi>Co</hi> 9.1.2. And againe, <hi>ye are our Epiſtle written in our hartes, which is vnderſtood and read of all men in that ye are manifeſted to be the epiſtle of Chriſt, miniſtred by us &amp; written not with ink but with the ſpirit of the liuing God, not in tables of ſtone but in fleſhy tables of the hart</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.2.3.</p>
            <p>Sith it is ſo, not to ſpeake &amp; put forth your ſelues in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of thes men is to ſpare ſpeach &amp; paynes for God him ſelfe &amp; for Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>Exod.</hi> 16 2. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.7. <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.16. If they are ſaid to deny bodily food aparrell &amp; lodging vnto Chriſt himſelfe, that deny theſe thinges to the leaſt of his elect, <hi>Math.</hi> 25.40. May not they much more be ſaid to ſpare ſpeech and paines for Chriſt, that ſpare their ſpeech &amp; paines for the everlaſting ſalvation of many thouſand ſoules. yea this cannot be denied, ſith all the Godly <hi>haue put on the Lord Ieſus</hi> Gal. 3.25. <hi>And are fleſh of his flesh and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18169:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>bone of his bone Ephe.</hi> 5.30.</p>
            <p>Finally let this argument the more prevaile with all men in regard of all that Chriſt Ieſus (whoſe cauſe this is ſhewed to be) hath ſuffered and done for vs.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It is alſo to be conſidered that the miniſtery of the Ghoſpell, is not only for earthly men, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> but alſo for heauen ly Angels. Therefore as the Cherubins were commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be ſett <hi>with their faces towards the Mercy ſeate. Exod.</hi> 25.20. as looking and liſtening after the Oracles of God that ſhould be geiven fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mercy ſeate to the Church, ſo it is not onely ſomewhat obſcurely ſaid concerning <hi>thoſe thinges that are shewed by them that preach the Goſpell by the holy Ghoſt, that the Angells doe deſier to behold the ſaide thinges,</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12. But leaſt any man ſhould thinke that to be vnderſtood onely of the accompliſhing of the matters preached in the finall, and perfect ſalvation of the elect &amp; whole Church; it is alſo plainely and moſt perſpecuouſly written, that one cheife end, purpoſe, and intent of <hi>prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ſaid Goſpell, and the vnſearchable riches of Chriſt in the Goſpell contained,</hi> and of making cleere <hi>vnto all men the fellowship of the myſtery of the Goſpell,</hi> was this, <hi>that now vnto principalities and powers in heavenly places,</hi> (that is unto An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels) <hi>might be knowe by the Church</hi> (not the great ſalvation of the Lord) <hi>but the manifold wiſdome of God. Epheſ.</hi> 3.10.</p>
            <p>To ſpeake therfore for the Goſpell &amp; for the ſincere mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery &amp; Miniſters therof, is to ſpeake not only for God, but alſo for the Angels. To ſpare ſpeaking &amp; other paines taking for the Goſpell and ſincere miniſtery thereof, is to ſpare ſpeaking and taking paynes for God himſelfe &amp; for his bleſſed Angels: and ſo conſequently, to provoke both the Lord himſelfe of heaven &amp; earth, and alſo the whole hoſt and army of heaven againſt vs. For, what elſe may
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18169:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>be hoped for where there will not ſo much as earnſt words be ſpoken for God, or for his Angels?</p>
            <p n="3">3 As <hi>Ioſeph</hi> having interpreted the Dreame of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> his cheife Butler touching his reconciliatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againe to the grace of <hi>Pharao,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and the recovery of his former pace of honorable ſervice before <hi>Pharao, deſiered him to haue him in remembrance when he shohold be ſo reconciled &amp; reſtored, Gen.</hi> 40 14. So it is recorded by the holy Ghoſt, &amp; acknowledged by the ſaid Butler, <hi>as a great fault, that he had not remebred</hi> Ioſeph <hi>but forgotto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him Gen.</hi> 40.23. &amp; 41.9. If it wereſo great a fault in <hi>Pharao</hi> his Butler, not to remember &amp; ſpeake for one <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> that had interpreted one dreame touching his reconcilement to a mortall Prince: and the recovery of an earthly preferment, (nether of which notwithſtading he knew not how long he ſhould enioye, at the moſt he could not enioye them any longer then during onely na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall life) how great then is the fault of all thoſe, that neg lect to ſpeake for many miniſters of the Goſpel, that haue not once but often, &amp; dayly interpreted many myſteries of God, toucing their reconciliatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with God himſelfe &amp; their everlaſting advancme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>in heavenly places Ephe.</hi> 2.6. <hi>To walke in white with Chriſt Ieſus, yea, to ſit alſo with him in his throne, as he himſelfe ſitteth in the throne of his Father? Apoc.</hi> 3.5. &amp; 21. Yea verely, as the fault of the <hi>Butler</hi> was the leſſe, becauſe being enlarged he had none to remember him of that duty, ſo the fault of thos ſhalbe the greater, that haue many dayly to put them in minde therof, and to provoke them thereunto, and yet for all that doe hold their peace.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The whole Army of Iſraell ſpake with great courage in behalfe of <hi>Ionathan</hi> thus, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
               <hi>Shall</hi> Ionathan <hi>dye who hath migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely delivered Iſraelle? God forbid. As the Lord liveth, there shall not one hayre of his head fall to the ground, for he hath wrought
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18169:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>with God this day.</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.45. Were this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people that lived under the Law, &amp; which had not had ſo plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full &amp; cleere inſtruction as is now revealed by the goſpel, were this common people (I ſay) ſo zealous for <hi>Ionathan</hi> in regard onely of a bodily deliverance, from bodily eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, whereof he had not been the author, but onely an inſtrument of God; and ſhall not this high Court of Parliament now aſſembled, being the cheife flower of this whole Realme of England, and repreſenting the whole Realme, be zealous and earneſt for many whom God hath uſed as his inſtruments, &amp; who haue wrought with God and dayly would ſo worke with God (if they may haue liberty) for the ſpirituall deliverance of many thouſandes from ſpirituall enimyes, even <hi>to turne them from darknes to light, and from the power of Sathan to God, that they may haue forgiunes of ſinnes, and inheritance among them that are ſainctified by faith in Chriſt. Actes</hi> 26.18?</p>
            <p n="5">5 It is not to be frogotten, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> with what courage &amp; good ſucceſſe <hi>Nchemiah</hi> ſpake for the materiall Ieruſalem to <hi>Artashasht</hi> an heathen and prophane King <hi>Neh.</hi> 2.2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as alſo how moſt vertuous &amp; noble <hi>Q. Eſther,</hi> being indeed provoked by poore <hi>Mordecai,</hi> adventured her ſelfe to ſpeake to the like conditioned King <hi>Ahashuerosh,</hi> in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of the old people of God the Iewes, for preventing of their bodily bloudſheed, notwithſtanding ſhe had not <hi>been called vnto the King in</hi> 30 <hi>dayes before, and notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding there were a law of the King, that whoſoever man or woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> should come vnto the King in the inward Court not called, should dye, except ſuch as to whom the King should haue held forth his golden rod.</hi> It is not (I ſay) to be forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly to be remembred, how notwithſtanding the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide danger and her former feare and weaknes in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18169:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>yet at the laſt ſhee promiſed <hi>Mordecai</hi> to adventure her ſelfe ſaying, <hi>If I perish, I perish:</hi> and how alſo after pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer and faſting of her ſelfe and her Ladyes, and of the reſt of the Iewes in <hi>Shushan</hi> for her, ſhe entred to the King &amp; ſpake for her people: and what gratious ſucceſſe ſhe had, notwithſtanding the power and might of their cheife ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, and his great grace and favour with the King. Did theſe perſons ſo adventure themſelues to ſpeake be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch Kings, and did the God of heaven giue ſuch gracious ſucceſſe in their attemptes? And ſhall Chriſtian Noble men &amp; gentlemen now aſſembled in high Court of Parliament, where they may ſpeake, and other in other places of authoritie and grace and favour with chriſtian Princes, feare to ſpeake for the people of God, to a chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an King, whoſe education from the Cradle in <hi>all</hi> pyety, former raigne and goverment, and religious profesſion hitherto, doe giue better encouragement: God forbid? And farr be <hi>all</hi> ſuch feare and cowardlines from <hi>all</hi> that profeſſe and know the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt. Yea, if there by any ſo fearefull and cowardly, let them ſeriouſly conſider the ſecond wordes and meſſage of <hi>Mordecai</hi> to <hi>Eſter. Thinke not that thou shalt eſcape in the Kings houſe more then all the Iewes: For is thou houldeſt thy peace at this tyme, comfort and deliverance shall appeare to the Iewes out of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, but thou and thy Fathers houſe shall perish. Who kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth whether thou art come to the Kingdome for ſuch a time. Eſter,</hi> 4.13. Let them (I ſay) wiſely and in the feare of God conſider this meſſage, to provoke themſelues to the more zeale and chriſtian bouldnes, with <hi>all</hi> humilitie and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie. Let them not thinke that they by their greatnes ſhall procure a better miniſtery of the Goſpell to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and their houſes then other haue. If it be reſtrained
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18169:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>from other, as of late it hath been, they ſhall not long en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioye more liberty thereof then other. Yea, if they at this tyme and in that place where there is ſuch fredome of ſpeech hold their peace, and doe not with <hi>all</hi> their guifts and graces of knowledg, wiſedome, zeale, compasſion, modeſty, and humility that may be, put forth themſelues in furtherance of the ſincere miniſtery of the Goſpell, and removing the lets and impediments thereof: ſuerly helpe may come in theſe thinges vnto the Church by ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes, but let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take heed that the Lord of hoſtes call them not to an accompt &amp; other reckoning for this their fearefulnes. Further to ad one other example breif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, If fearefull <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea</hi> went boldly to <hi>Pilate</hi> &amp; asked the body of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> And if <hi>Nicodemus</hi> (before as feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as the ſaid <hi>Ioſeph</hi>) joyned with him in the honorable buriall therof when Chriſt was dead, and the whole ſtate being enimyes vnto him, had now prevailed and gotten that which long they had laboured for againſt him, yea, when all the <hi>Diſciples</hi> had forſaken him, and ſome of the cheifeſt Champions had denyed him, Oh how diſhono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable with men, and inexſcuſable and vnanſwerable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God ſhall it be, that ſo many having learned more of Chriſt then either <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> or all the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> themſelues had then learned, and having alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore boldly profeſſed and promiſed much for him, and living in a kingdome profesſing Chriſt and maintainying his Goſpell, and under a moſt gratious &amp; religious King, and being in place of freedome of ſpeech and now alſo aſſembled cheifely and principally for that end (for what are <hi>all</hi> ſtatuts for the Common wealth without regard of the Church) how diſhonrable (I ſay) with men, and how inexſcuſable and vnanſwerable before God &amp; his Sonne
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18169:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Ieſus Chriſt when he ſhall come to judgment ſhall it be, that ſuch perſons in ſuch a kingdome, vnder ſuch a Kinge in ſuch a place, at ſuch a time, ſhall not dare to ſpeake for whole Chriſt Ieſus, riſen againe from the dead, aſcended into the heavens, there ſitting in all power, glory and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie? Yea finally being readie to come to judge both the quicke and the dead, both men an Angels? Oh therefore yee that loue this Lord Ieſus, Chriſt, take heed of ſuch fearefulnes, yea, feare ſo to be a fraide of ſpeaking for him, for his Goſpell and for his ſervantes.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Let the great heavines of many Congregations, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Men, Weomen, Children, Maſters &amp; ſervants, of all ages and conditions, be pittifully conſidered. God regarded the weeping of bond <hi>Hagar,</hi> and reprobate <hi>Iſhmaell</hi> in the want of the water of this life. <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.16. He graciouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected the poore women that complayning of the cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their Husbands in forſaking them, <hi>and vexing them</hi> by takinge other wyues, <hi>had covered his Aulter with their teares. Malac.</hi> 2.13.14.</p>
            <p>The Lord Ieſus alſo pytied the people, yea, his bowel; yerned within him, to ſee them ſcattered as ſheepe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſhepheard: <hi>Math.</hi> 9.36. <hi>Mar.</hi> 6.34. yea he did graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly reſpect the petitions of many touching the bodily miſeryes of their children, frends, and ſervants, yea the ſuits of ſome for bodily comfort of their children though themſelues were not of the children of <hi>Iſraell</hi> but Heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and Cananits, and litle better in that reſpect then Doggs. <hi>Math.</hi> 15.22. How then ſhould the ſpirituall miſeryes of many thowſands, partly already deprived, and partly like to be deprived of their faithfull Paſtors, who haue broken the bread: and powered out the water of eternall life vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, and performed the dueties as it were of loving
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18169:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>bands, and who by ſuch Paſtors and Preachers, <hi>haue been turned from darknes to light, and delivered from the power of Sathan vnto God,</hi> and who now therefore in the want of them, doe cover the Lords Aulter with teares, and make lamentable mone (as the <hi>Turtle Doue,</hi> that hath loſt her mate) for help to themſelues and theirs, againſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and future ſpirituall calamities, how I ſay ought all theſe things to wring and wreſt, pity and compasſion fro all in authority to wards them? O therefore let not their mone and lamentation be neglected. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 To regard theſe Miniſters hitherto ſpoken of, is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the whole land. For it is not to be doubted, but that it may be ſpoken of them: as well as of ſome other, that, <hi>they are the Chariots and Horſemen of England,</hi> as the like is acknowledged for Iſraell, not onely of <hi>Elia</hi> by <hi>Eliſha,</hi> 2. <hi>king</hi> 2.12 but alſo of <hi>Eliſha by Ioaſh</hi> a wicked King of Iſrael, 2. <hi>King.</hi> 13.14. <hi>If God be with vs who can be againſt us;</hi> Rom. 8 31. And if the <hi>Almightie be our defence</hi> (as <hi>Eliphas</hi> ſpeaketh to <hi>Iob,</hi> Iob 22.25.) We cannot but be in peace and ſafity.</p>
            <p>Now God hath not promiſed to be with any for their defence, but ſuch as receiue his Goſpell. In the Miniſtery alſo of the Goſpell, conſiſteth the wealth and honor of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very people, <hi>Pro.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 46.12. And the glory of every kingdome, as the glory of Iſraell did in the <hi>Arke.</hi> 1. Sam. 4.21.22. And the peace of Nations. For therefore as well as for other reſpects, the Goſpell is called the Goſpell of peace <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6.15. compared with <hi>Iſai.</hi> 2.4. and 11.6. and 65.25. Finally, the whole outward proſperity of all Kings &amp; kingdomes conſiſteth principally in the pure worſhip of God, and the menaes that commends the ſame 2. <hi>Chro</hi> 14.14.17.10.27.6.24.26. 2. King. 18.7. Therefore they cannot be faithfull to Kings &amp; kingdomes, neither to themſelues
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18169:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>that neglect the true worſhip of God &amp; the meanes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Therefore alſo as <hi>Eſter</hi> ſaid of thoſe that provoked <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haſhuerosh</hi> againſt the Iewes, ſo may it be ſaid of all thoſe that perſwade the ſuppresſion of the Goſpell and of the miniſters thereof, <hi>Such adverſaries cannot recompence the Kings loſſe Eſter</hi> 7.4.</p>
            <p>If therefore ye will not reſpect the ſtate of Miniſters, their wiues and children, yet reſpect your ſelues, your wiues and children, yea, our King and whole kingdome, even touching the outward eſtate of your ſelues &amp; yours, of King and kingdome. And if yee loue the ſafitie, peace, wealth, and glorie of King, and Kingdome, and of your ſelues and youres, then ſpeake &amp; doe, what you all, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of you may, for the Goſpell &amp; miniſtery therof.</p>
            <p n="8">8 It is the duety of all Princes &amp; Magiſtrates, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> and alſo of their Courtes, <hi>to execute iuſtice and iudgment in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and to deliuer the oppreſſed &amp;c. Ier.</hi> 21.12.22.2. eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to do iuſtice towards the ſoules of men. Therefore this eſpecially doth belong to this high Court of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament as being the higheſt Court we haue for iuſtice and iudgment vpon earth. As Abraham therefore ſaid vnto God, <hi>Shall not the Iudge of all the world doertght Gen.</hi> 18.25. ſo ſay I to this preſent court, ſhall not the higheſt Court of all this, Kingdome doe right? Yea this is the more at this preſent to be conſidered, becauſe this iuſtice that now I ſpeake of, is not only the Iuſtice of God, but alſo of this Land. For it is abundantly of late proued, that all the late proceedinges, againſt the miniſters, in repreeſing of their miniſtery, and in depriving them of their free houldes, is contrary to the lawes of this kingdome, both to <hi>Charta Magna,</hi> and alſo to many ſtatutes.</p>
            <p>The ſame is to be vnderſtood of the oath <hi>ex officio</hi> of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18169:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the late Canons, and of diuers other thines. It is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo againſt reaſon, that the beſeſt Cobler and Tinker can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be eiected from his free hould of but ten ſhillings by the yeare, but by a Iury of 12 men, and before ſome of his Maieſties Iudges in ſollemnte forme of lawe, and that the miniſters and Ambaſſadors of Chriſt Ieſus, in the mat ters of eternall life, ſhould be caſe out of their free hould, of what worth foeuer, by one man only, and not only without any Iury, but alſo without any complaint or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation againſt them.</p>
            <p>If it be obiected that this that I haue ſaid to be the iuſtice of this kingdome, is but the opinion of ſome priuat per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, let the miniſters finde fauor with this high Court of iuſtice, to haue the former canſes in the ſaid Court de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated, as many the like haue bin hearetofore &amp; daily are. Shall priuat cauſes be reſepected by you, yea ſhall matters of purveyors and ſuch like of ſmall moment for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, come before you, and be ſo largely diſcus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and handeled by you, and ſhall not ſo many publique cauſes of ſo many, of ſuch quality, and for the Church be regarded? yea not the cauſe of God him ſelfe? ſhall God and his ſonne Chriſt Ieſus, in the cauſe of his Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell and miniſters thereof, ſtand as it wear at your parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment houſe dore knocking, and craving to be let in, &amp; to haue their cauſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heard, &amp; ſhall not your dore be opened? Beware of this, leaſt ye knock alſo at heaven dore, &amp; there be none found to open, or to anſwere vnto you.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/>
            <p n="9">9 May if further pleaſe them to whom this preſent writing is directed, to call to minde the promiſes made to them, that ſhew any kindnes to any of the Children of God &amp; diſciples of Chriſt, eſpecially to any <hi>Prophet in in the name of a Prophet Mat.</hi> 10.41. As alſo to conſider <hi>that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18169:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>God is not vnrighteous, that he ſhould forget ſuch worke &amp; labor of loue. Heb.</hi> 6.10. but that <hi>he is faithfull that hath promiſed. Heb.</hi> 10.23. and that <hi>God is not as man, that he should ly nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as the ſonne of man, that he should repent: hath he ſaid it &amp; shall not he do it? and hath he ſpoken, and shall not he accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish it? Numb.</hi> 23.19.</p>
            <p>He that made <hi>Saule,</hi> (though vnnaturall to his owne children, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.49. and a cruell murderer of the preiſts of the Lord. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 22 18.) to ſhew mercy to the <hi>Kenits,</hi> (as were the rocke to yeeld water) 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.6. For the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of <hi>Iethro,</hi> (otherwiſe called <hi>Keni,</hi> Iudg. 1.16) towards the <hi>Iſraelits,</hi> in giueing onely good counſell to <hi>Moſes,</hi> for the better outward goverment of the <hi>Iſraelits,</hi> 400. yeares before <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.17. Shall he forget, the kindnes, that ſhall be ſhewed to the Miniſters of the Goſpell, and to the people committed vnto them, and depending upon them, for the food and ſalvation of their ſoules?</p>
            <p>Was the kindnes of the <hi>Shunamite,</hi> towards one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eliſha,</hi> plentifully recompenced; 1. by the guift of a Sonne after long barrennes; 2 by reſtoryng her ſaid ſonne to life being dead, 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 4-16.3 by forewarning her of a famine to come, and admoniſhing her, to provide for her ſelfe <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.1. 4 by directing her, by God his gratious providence, to come with petition to the <hi>King,</hi> for reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of her lands (that had been ſeiſed in her abſence to the Kings uſe) at that very inſtante, when <hi>Gehazi</hi> was tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the King the great acts of his <hi>M. Eliſha,</hi> and particular ly how he had raiſed this womans ſonne from death to life: (by which her commyng in ſuch a ſeaſon ſhe preſent ly obtayned, not onely her lands, but alſo all the meane profites that in time of her peregrination, had been taken by the Kings receiver:) was (I ſay) ſuch little kindnes of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18169:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>this woman, to one prophet, ſo plentifully recompenſed; and ſhall not the favour that is ſhewed to many Miniſters of the Goſpell, (the leaſt wherof, for office is greater then <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> who notwithſtanding was greater then any prophet, and then whom there was not a greater, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the ſonnes begotten of weomen, <hi>Math.</hi> 11.9.) ſhall not (I ſay) ſuch kindnes towards ſuch Miniſters as are in ſo great reckening with God, be reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred &amp; rewarded?</p>
            <p n="10">10 On the contrary conſider, who hath ſaid, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> 
               <hi>Touch not myne annoynted, and doe my prophets no harme: pſal.</hi> 105.15; As alſo what is threatened, to them that doe the leaſt harme, to the leaſt children of God, even in their outward ſtates, Yea, what God commaunded to be written againſt the <hi>Amalikits,</hi> and ſware to performe, onely for reſiſting his people, in their iorney towards the earthly <hi>Canaan,</hi> which was but a type of the heavenly. <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.14.15. And what alſo afterward (even 400. yeares after the premiſes) he cauſed to be executed by <hi>Saule</hi> againſt them, <hi>without any pity or compasſion, towards any man, woman, infante, or ſuckling Oxe, Sheepe, cattell, or Aſſe</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.3. Was it ſo heinous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, to hinder his people in their iourney to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the earthly <hi>Canaan,</hi> &amp; ſhall it be a light thing with men now, not to further the elect in their meanes of, and iourney vnto, the heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> tipically prefigured, <hi>by that earthly?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the Lord did alſo ſware, <hi>by the excellencie of</hi> Iacob, <hi>that ſuerly he would never forget the crueltie, that was excerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the rich men of</hi> Iudea, <hi>againſt the poore of the land, in their outward ſtate, yea, that the very land ſhould tremble, and that every one ſhould mourne that dwelled therin &amp;c. For the the ſaid ſinne. Amos</hi> 8.7. Will the ſame Lord then, which is alwayes the ſame in Iuſtice, as well as in mercy, lightly
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18169:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>paſſe by any cruelty towardes the ſoules of his people?</p>
            <p>Let not the ſtates aſſembled in this High Court of Parliament, or in any place of authority, grace, and favor, where their word ſpoken in his place, <hi>May be like vnto Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of gould with pictures of ſilver, Pro.</hi> 25.11. Let them not (I ſay) waſh their handes of this argument, becauſe they haue no hand in any proceeding againſt the Miniſters, or in reſtrainying of their miniſtery: fith it is all one ſo to pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceed &amp;c. And not to heelp them that are ſo proceeded againſt by other eſpecially when power is in their hands to helpe. For it muſt never be forgotten, which is written for an everlaſting truth, and a perpetuall inſtruction, <hi>(Curſe ye Meroz: (ſayd the Angell of the Lord) curſe the inbabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant thereof, becauſe they came not to heelp the Lord, to heelp the Lord againſt the mightie. Iudges</hi> 5.23. In which place this is likewiſe worthy the obſervation of all men, that they are eſteemed not to help the Lord, that came not out to help his people. If there were ſo fearefull a curſe pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced by the Angell of the Lord gainſt them that did not helpe his people, againſt the mightie enimyes of their outward ſtate, may they think themſelues ſecure &amp; with out daunger, that heelp not the Lord and his people, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the mighty that oppugne the everlaſtying ſalvation of their ſoules? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> 
            </p>
            <p n="11">11 <hi>Pharao</hi> in the tyme of dearth, provided at his owne coſt for the Idolatrous Preiſts of <hi>Egypt,</hi> that they might not fell their land: <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.22. Shall then ſo chriſtian a king dome, as this long tyme hath been, in the time of plentie proceed ſo hardly againſt the painfull miniſters of the Goſpell, that they, their wiues and children ſhall weepe agd mourne for want? And will no man open his month in their behalfe? Were the <hi>Mouncks</hi> and <hi>Friers</hi> at the diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18169:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>of their Idolatrous houſes, (in the twilight of the Goſpell,) provided for duringe their liues, though they never had done any good? And ſhall the miniſters of the Goſpell, that haue converted many to God, and ſpent themſelues, and waſted their patrimony, firſt, in fitting themſelues for the worke of the miniſtery, and after by their ſufferings and troubles, ſo that they haue nothing left for their comfort in their age, be neglected? Though this hath not been regarded, by thoſe that deprived the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet farr be it, from this moſt Honorable Court, that any heart would be found therein ſo hard and ſtony, as not with commiſeration to pity them. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> 
            </p>
            <p n="12">12 Much alſo may the prayers of ſuch miniſters for this Court of Parliament, and for every ſtate and degree ther of, and for other, be regarded: <hi>for the prayer of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous availeth much if it be fervent,</hi> Iames 5.16. And the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers of the Saints are compared <hi>To Harpes &amp; golden vialls f<hi rend="sup">u</hi>ll of odours &amp;c. Apoc.</hi> 5.8. God would haue <hi>Abimelech King of Gerar,</hi> to make ſuch accompt of this argument, that for the ſame he would haue him <hi>to uſo Abraham the better, Gen</hi> 20.7.</p>
            <p>Nether did the Apoſtle <hi>Paule</hi> onely; for this cauſe, moſt earneſtly craue the prayers of the meaneſt chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, in thoſe Churches to which he wrote: but alſo wicked <hi>Pharao</hi> did eaneſtly deſire the prayers of <hi>Moſes and Aaron, Exod.</hi> 8.8. <hi>Darius</hi> alſo, though an heathen King, did there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore commaund all things neceſſary, for the building of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> to be a boundantly miniſtred to the Iewes, that they might <hi>pray for the Kings life, and for his ſonnes, Ezra</hi> 6 10. How much more then ought ſuch chriſtian aſſemblies as this preſent High Court of Parliament is: to labonr the more, for the comfort of God his children, eſpecially
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18169:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>his faithfull miniſters, that thereby they may be incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to prayer the more earneſtly, for them and theirs.</p>
            <p n="13">13 Suerly (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>The harveſt is great,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> 
               <hi>and the laborers are fewe, praye ye therefore the Lord of the harueſt, that he would thruſt forth laborers into his harveſt. Math.</hi> 9.37.38. Will our <hi>Saviour,</hi> haue all to pray the Lord of the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, that he would thruſt forth laborers into his harveſt, and may any men then, by head &amp; ſhoulders thruſt labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers out of his harveſt? It would be accompted madnes, for a man to thruſt laborers out of his owne harveſt, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his harveſt is raddy for the ſickle, and he hath not laborers enough; But it is impietie to thruſt laborers out of the Lord his harveſt, eſpecially ſuch, as whom himſelfe had before thruſt forth into his harveſt, furniſhyng them with ſickle and all other thinges neceſſary? And laſtly, ſuch as had done good ſervice in his harveſt? Againe, will our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, haue men onely to praye the Lord of the harveſt, for thruſting forth of laborers into his harveſt, and will he may they thinke, that they are onely to praye for their dayly bread, and that they need to doe nothing elſe for the getting thereof.</p>
            <p n="14">14 <hi>Whoſoeuer</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>ſhall be aſhamed of me and of my wordes,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> 
               <hi>of them shall the ſonne of man be a shamed, when he shall come in his glory, and in the glory of the father, &amp; of the holy Angels: Lue.</hi> 9.26. Is this to be underſtood onely of the tyme of perſecution, and not alſo and much more, of the dayes of peace? Or are not they a ſhamed of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and of his wordes, that will not ſpeake for him and his word? Nay let the contrary branch of the oppoſition tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching the promiſe, made by our <hi>Saviour</hi> for the confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of them <hi>before his Father which is in heaven, that shall
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18169:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>confeſſe him before men,</hi> ſuppreſſe this vaine imagination: Laſtly touching this poynt will they not be a ſhamed of Chriſt, but confeſſe him and his words before Tyrants, in the time of fiery triall, that will not ſhew themſelues zealous for Chriſt and his wovds, before a State favourig and profesſing Chriſt &amp; his words, in the dayes of peace? Truely God by his almightie power, and rich grace may mightely ſtrengthen ſuch men in the dayes of trouble, (notwithſtanding their preſent feare and weaknes) but certainly in reaſon this is litle to be hoped for. Let no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore flatter or deceaue himſelfe with any ſuch poore, ſimple, and ſhiftfull conceite.</p>
            <p n="15">15 Your zeale touching the Papiſts for more ſecuritie againſt them heerafter, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> that therby they may be the more eaſily converted from their damnable hereſies; is worthy everlaſtyng renowne. But may it alſo pleaſe you to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, to what end there ſhall be more ſevere lawes made, for the bringing of them to Church, if there ſhall not lik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be proviſion, that when they come there they may haue ſuch miniſters as ſhalbe able ſubſtantially, and ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to confute their hereſies, and to inſtruct them in the truth: and not ſuch, as againſt whom in reſpect of their in ſufficiency and weakenes, they ſhalbe able to take excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: yea whom alſo they ſhall deride: yea, and finally, by whom they ſhall be more confirmed in their hereſies: or at the leaſt the more, hardened againſt the truth. Will any man ſay ther may be ſuffieient miniſters enough, though all thoſe that are called refractary, and vnconformable be expelled? I hope the wiſedome of the meaneſt of your Honorable aſſembly is ſuch, that he will heare this an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times, before he will beleiue it once: For ſith all that now are, and were before any proceeding againſt thoſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18169:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>before mentioned, were not enough, ſufficiently to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh every Congregation, what will the paucity be. when from thoſe, ſo many hundreds as able as any other ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be detracted.</p>
            <p n="16">16 Tovching the matters of trouble, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> and moleſtation to the miniſters hitherto mentioned, viz. Subſcription, Ceremonyes, the ſtrict obſervation of the booke, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Conformity, all men know, what diviſion &amp; conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ther hath been betwixt the miniſters of the word in this kingdome, and their brethren, as in other Churches reformed, ſo eſpecially in the former part of his Majeſties Dominion <hi>Scotland;</hi> and what hath been written by one parte (eſpecially by the conformable part) in diſgrace and reproch of the other. But eſpecially, great hath been the contention and controverſie heere at home: much more indeed for &amp; about thes things, then for or <hi>about any poynt of Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is evident, not onely by moſt bitter invectiue ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mons, private raylings, and publicke diſgracefull bookes againſt them: (the moſt Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formitans thinking that they never preach, ſpeake, or write any thing well, except in their preaching, talke &amp; writing, they ſcourge thoſe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they call Puritan, preſciſe, ſciſmaticall, and refractary mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters) but alſo by the actuall ſeveritie againſt them. For it may be trulie ſaid, that in one yeare, and in one <hi>Dioceſſe,</hi> more haue been for theſe cauſes ſuſpended and deprived, then in full 46 yeares throughout the whole Realme of <hi>England,</hi> either for vnſufficiencie, or for any matter of ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall: albe it it cannot be denyed, that in ſome one <hi>Dioceſſe,</hi> their are more ignorant &amp; ſcandolous miniſters worthy of deprivation, then there are conformable miniſters in all <hi>Dioceſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:18169:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>By this controverſie and contention among the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, ther hath been no leſſe diſſention and alination of mindes and hartes, betwixt other of his Majeſtiesſubjects for the ſame things: yea, much ſeperation of many from their miniſters, as likwiſe betwixt themſelues. Now how dangerous this is for his Majeſtie and the whole land, as it doth appeare by the encreaſe and courage of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon adverſaryes the Papiſts, according as the miniſters and people for thoſe cauſes haue been moleſted and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graced, ſo it is further evident by reaſon. Becauſe as the concord, peace, and good agreement is a principall part of the ſtrenght of a King and kingdome, ſo their diſcord and contention, cannot but be daungerous for King and kingdome. For our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelfe (ſpeaking according to the common ſpeech of other) ſaith, <hi>That a kingdome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided againſt it ſelfe, cannot ſtand.</hi> Marc. 3.24.</p>
            <p>What is therefore to be done in this caſe? How may theſe controverſies and contentions be well pacified, and beſt compounded? Verily by inmitating therin God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>the God of peace.</hi> For as he is and muſt be acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged beſt of all, ſo heerin alſo, he hath given vs the beſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, the beſt patterne. What is that? When he faw the great diviſion and hatred betwixt the Iewes &amp; the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, <hi>he tooke away the partition wall betwixt them,</hi> which was alſo called by the name of <hi>hatred,</hi> becauſe for it the Iewes had hated the Gentiles, and the Gentile likewiſe the Iewes. What was the partition wall? <hi>The law of commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements ſtanding in ordinaunces,</hi> that is in Ceremonyes, which he himſelfe had given to the Iewes. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.14.15 For thereby, cannot be underſtood the morall law, which from the beginning had as well concerned the Gentiles, as the Iewes; But the Ceremoniall law being that, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18169:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>wherof, the Iewes in pride had contemned the Gen tils, and for which the Gentils likewiſe, in no leſſe mallice had envied the Iewes, as having ſuch a law by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues as for the which, they neither would not might commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with the Gentils in their heatheniſh worſhip: the Lord therefore did altogether remoue the ſame, that ſo not onely they <hi>which were once farr from God, might be made neere by the bloud of Chriſt</hi> (whereby the partition wall was broken downe) but that <hi>they alſo that had ben before twaine, might be made one</hi> (as it were two houſes made one, by breaking downe of one wall, or two feildes layd into one by taking away of one hedg) <hi>that ſo there might be peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord might haue communicated the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the Iewes vnto the Gentils, or geiven new vnto both. But ſith he made this peace onely by removing thoſe Ceremonyes together, that himſelfe had once in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, and did not ordayne any in their place, then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider I (beſeech you) in your godly wiſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es, how much more it behoueth all thoſe Ceremonyes and ordinances, which were onely invented by man, to be vtterly remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, having eſpecially no neceſſary uſe, but being rather bones of contention betwixt brethren, and children of the ſame Father and Moother, and coheyres of the ſame inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: as alſo people of the ſame Nation, and ſubjects of the ſame King and Soveraigne. Yea conſider (I beſeech you againe) the more ſeriouſly, how neceſſary it will be, thus to make peace, not onely becauſe this. peace will be exceedingly beneficiall (as hath been ſhewed) to King &amp; kingdome, (eſpecially the common adverſaryes ſo now combining themſelues againſt vs) but alſo becauſe it wil be a worke moſt acceptable to God. For <hi>Bleſſed are the peace makers for they ſhall be called the children of God. Math.</hi> 5.9</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:18169:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="17">17 In the next place (that I may heape vp many thinges to geather, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> and contriue many arguments into one) I doe offer to your wiſe and godly conſiderations, the works of God a mongſt vs: his works of Iuſtice, and his works of mercy: togeather with the ends for the which he hath wrought them before vs, and the vſes, which he would haue vs to make of them. Firſt therefore be yee pleaſed to call to minde, the late mightie and fearefull peſtilence, wherby in all places (almoſt) of the land, but cheifely here in London, the Lord <hi>made heapes upon heapes.</hi> Doth the Lord chaſtiſe particular perſons, <hi>that he may teach them in his law, Pſal.</hi> 94, 12. Drawe them neerer vnto him, <hi>and make them</hi> more plentifully <hi>partaker of his holines?</hi> Heb. 12.10. Yea, and <hi>that they may be more zealous &amp; amend.</hi> Revel. 3.19 And are not theſe as well the ends, why he chaſtiſeth whole States, Churches and kingdomes, as the ſinnes of whole States, Churches and Kingdomes, are the cauſes that firſt moue him ſo to chaſtiſe them? Yea, is not this the more to be conſidered, becauſe this rod of God doth ſtill remaine and linger, as here in <hi>London,</hi> ſo alſo in divers other places of the land? For doth not the Lord heereby intimate vnto vs, that yet that is not performed by vs which he looked for from vs?</p>
            <p>Againe, is it altogether to be neglected, that he hath ſo mittigated this his ſeverity towards vs as he hath? And that he hath in parte commaunded his Angell to put vp his ſword, and not to ſinite ſo many as before he had do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e. And doth not the Lord by ſmyting vs in ſuch ſorte, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after that if for all this we ſhew no better fruits of amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>he will plague us yet ſcaven tymes worſe?</hi> Levit. 26.18. By healing vs alſo in part, doth he not admoniſh vs, that if we do not yet repent, but conrinewe <hi>ſtill to ſinne againſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18169:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>him, a worſe thing ſhall come vnto us? Iohn</hi> 5.14.</p>
            <p>O ye that doe now repreſent the body of this land, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of this matter.</p>
            <p>What ſhall I heere ſpeake of our late great danger, by the late moſt bloudie, horrible, vnnaturall and monſtrous conſpiracy of the Papiſts; as againſt all in generall, ſo ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially againſt you that are now aſſembled, in this high Court of Parliament? Would the Lord haue every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to provoke his <hi>owne ſoule, to prayſe the Lord, for redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming his ſoule from the graue</hi> Pſa. 103.4. And would he not haue the whole land, and ſpecially you that are now aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in high court of Parliament repreſenting the whole land, and in ſpeciall manner delivered, to enter into ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſultation &amp; deliberation with your ſelues, <hi>what to render vnto the Lord, for all his benifits towards you? pſa.</hi> 116.12</p>
            <p>Though <hi>Hezekiah</hi> having recovered health, went firſt into the houſe of God, and made there a pſalme of thanks givinge for his recovery, which yet remaineth in holy writ, as an everlaſting moniment of his thankfulnes; yet becauſe in other things, he was not generally ſo circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and carefull, of all obedience to God as he ſhould haue been, <hi>but his heart was lift vp with in him,</hi> it is ſayd that <hi>he rendred not vnto the Lord, according unto the reward beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vppon him;</hi> and that therefore <hi>wrath came from the Lord againſt him, aganſt Ieruſalem, and againſt Iuda.</hi> 2 Chro. 32.25 So let this be conſidred, that yee may provoke yourſelues to the more publike teſtimony of thankfulnes, for our late publike delivera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. And becauſe <hi>mercy</hi> (even towards the bodyes of men) <hi>is more deſired then ſacrifice,</hi> and that therefore mercy towards their ſoules, is much more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vnto God, (for which cauſe it is there ſaid, that <hi>the Lord doth</hi> alſo <hi>more deſier the knowledg of God, then burnt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18169:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>offrings.</hi> Hoſ. 6.6.) Therefore alſo as God his goodnes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the whole land is knowne to all the world, ſo let all the world knowe, and let all ages to come be witneſſes, of our thankfulnes for the ſame, by your preſent mercy towards the Church. He that biddeth vs <hi>to call vpon him in the day of our trouble,</hi> and promiſeth to <hi>deliver us,</hi> requireth alſo <hi>that we ſhould glorifie him.</hi> pſal. 50.15. How much more then ought we to glorifie him, being in the day of our trouble delivered, before we called vpon him?</p>
            <p>Verely (moſt Honorable aſſembly) in this reſpect our deliverance is the greater, then the deliverance either of the Iewes from the bloudy intent of <hi>Haman,</hi> or of our ſelues in the yeare 1588. For the Lord did not worke thos deliverances with out the meanes of prayer and faſting: but this, his owne right hand hath brought to paſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that ever we did open our lipps vnto him in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe. Yea, herein is our deliverance alſo the greater, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe though the miſcheife plotted againſt vs was but bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dily, yet the miſcheife plotted againſt our and all poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was ſpirituall, even to haue reduced them, to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer bondage of popiſh blindnes, ſuperſtition, and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, ſo to haue periſhed everlaſtingly: and therfore we that ſhould haue been conſumed touching our bodyes, and outward ſtates in this intended maſſacre (if it had procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) ſhould haue ben much better, then they that ſhould haue lived. As it be-longeth therefore to all at all tymes to glorifie God for this great deliverance, ſo ſpecially it be-longeth to you that are now aſſembled in this high-Court of Parliament.</p>
            <p>The Lord careth not for any obſervation of a day on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in remembrance of his mercyes, nor for bate words in commendation and celebration of his goodnes, except
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18169:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:18169:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:18169:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>that otherwiſe we doe <hi>diſpoſe our way a right:</hi> For this is the beſt <hi>prayſe whereby he is glorified.</hi> pſa. 50.25. Yea even now, and at this Sesſion, doth the Lord require this of you. For hath not his hand of ſicknes in many places continued, &amp; doth it not ſtill hoover over vs, from before the firſt ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moning of this Parliament, to this preſent Sesſion? And did not God reveale his mercy revealing the late treaſon, and delivering vs from it, immediatly before the laſt Ses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that your meeting might be proroged, whereby in the time of Interim, ye might haue the more leaſure, the better to deliberat and conſult, what at this your aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly might moſt make for the glory of his name, and the good of his Church? And will ye now diſſolue your met ting without doeing of further matter in that behalfe, then yet ye haue done.</p>
            <p>Againe, are not many of you auncient, and in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect never againe to be of any other Parliament? which alſo of the youngeſt and luſtieſt of you knoweth, either that he ſhall liue to an other Parliament, or to another Sesſion of this Parliament? Or if he ſhall liue to another Parliament, that he ſhall be choſen to be againe thereof: Or livyng to another Sesſion of this Parliament, that he ſhall haue health and ſtrenght to be preſent thereat. Are not ſome worthy men, that were at the former Sesſions of this Parliament, now at reſt with the Lord? Yea are not ſome other that were livyng &amp; in health at the time of the laſt Sesſion, now alſo (before the beginyng of this Sesſion) gathered to their Fathers.</p>
            <p>Yea further, becauſe divers of the minſters deprived and ſilenced (being partly very aged) &amp; partly conſumed with godly greife, (not ſo much for the owne troubles, (as for the deſolation of the Churches, both preſently
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18169:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſeene, and for future tymes by the preſent to be progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticated, in as much as many moſt vnworthy perſons are thruſt into their places, (in which conſideration, as <hi>Eliſha</hi> wept, by me ſpirit of prophecie, to fore ſee the miſerable havocke that <hi>Hazeel</hi> ſhould make of the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> touching their bodies, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.11.12. So what chriſtian heart can refraine weepyng and bleeding, to fore thinke of the ſpirituall ſpoyle, that will be made in the Church by blind guides, corrupt teachers, and careles: yea wicked and vngodly Paſtors) becauſe (I ſay) many faithfull mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters deprived and ſilenced, partly by age, and partly by godly greife, are ſo neere the finiſhing of their raſe, that the ground for their graue is in a manner all ready meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, therefore ye that are the Lords worthies now aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in this High and Honorable Court, doe that, that is to be done by you, for the glory of God, and comfort of his Churches and Miniſters, with the more ſpeed and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition, that ſuch ſervants of God as are ſo neere their end, may yet be ſomewhat revived and comforted before their end, and bleſſe you and yours before they dye, and ſo take their leaues alſo of you and yours, with the more peace and ioye to their owne ſoules.</p>
            <p>As your houſe of parliament at the laſt Sesſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſhould pasſiuely haue been the houſe of blood, yea the fountaine (in ſome ſorte) of blood, that even from thence ſhould haue flowed ſtreames and rivers of blood through out the whole land, ſo let it at this Sesſion be actiuely the houſe of comfort, yea a fountaine of comfort, that from thence may flowe a river (as it were the river of God) and a floude of ſpirituall comfort, ioye and gladnes to all the land. To all the land? Yea to all Nations that know the Lord and call upon his name: yea to all poſterity. As the 26
<pb facs="tcp:18169:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>firſt day of the laſt Sesſion ſhould haue been, <hi>a day of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and of blacknes, a day of cloudes and of obſcuritie</hi> (as <hi>Ioel</hi> ſpeaketh chap. 2.2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> let the laſt day of this Sesſion be a bright and cleare ſuneſhine day, a day of light, a day of comfort and refr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing from the Lord. As the Lords eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, the blood and mercyles papiſts (merciles to them ſelues in mur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing themſelues heertofore &amp; of late, and therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> more mercyles vnto other) as theſe men would ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> made themſelues, as a fire to devoure all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d as a flame to burne vp all be hind them. Ioel</hi> 2.3. So be you at are the children of God, &amp; <hi>ſhould therefore be mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s your Father alſo is mercifull Luc.</hi> 6.36. Be ye (I ſay) as there the <hi>rayne; even as the firſt and the latter rayne,</hi> Ioel 2.4. As their wrath ſhould haue been <hi>like the roaring of a-Lyon,</hi> (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaketh of <hi>the wrath of a King</hi>) ſo let your favour be (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaketh of <hi>the favor of a King</hi>) <hi>like the dewe upon the graſſe.</hi> Pro. 19.12.</p>
            <p>By this mercy that hetherto I haue (as it were at the barre of your Iuſtice) pleaded for, and provoked you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, ye ſhall not only treaſure up comfort to your ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the day of your death, when ye ſhall moſt ſtand in neede of comfort, but ye ſhall alſo make your old age the more honorable; yea after your dayes heare ended, your name and memory will be honorable with all poſteritie. Wherfore did <hi>Deborah</hi> ſay <hi>that Iael the wife of Heber ſhould be bleſſed aboue other women, yea bleſſed aboue other women dwel ling in tents?</hi> Iudg. 5.24. Becauſe <hi>with an hammer ſhee had driven a nayle</hi> ſo deepe into the head of <hi>Siſera</hi> ſleeping in her tent, that he did never a wake.</p>
            <p>If ſuch a ſentence of bleſſednes were prophecied of <hi>Iael,</hi> for makeing away only an outward enimy of the out word ſtate of the Church, how much more ſhall ye be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18169:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>bleſſed, yea bleſſed aboue many former Parliament men, if as ſome haue made a beginning of the deſolation of the whore of Rome in theſe landes, ſo ye ſhall make perfect that beginning, and vtterly take away whatſoever of her ornaments yet remayning, wherwith ſhe and her prieſts were wont to be decked, and are yet decked, &amp; wherwith alſo her Idols were wont to be worſhipped, and are yet worſhipped? And if as other haue already (in ſome ſort) begunne to driue the nayle into the head of the Archeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my (next vnder Sathan himſelfe) of the ſpirituall ſtate of the Church, ſo ye ſhall alſo driue the ſame further? Yea if likewiſe as the Papiſts comforted themſelues tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching their contrived and hoped for deſtruction of our perſons, and of our religion, ſaying (in dreaming ſort) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelues, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid to the Iſraclits, <hi>theſe men &amp; this religion which ye haue hitherto ſeene, ye shall never ſee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,</hi> ſo likwiſe ye by the ſword of the word of the Lord, and of your authority, (as it were <hi>by the ſword of the Lord and of Gidcon,</hi> Iudg. 7.20.) if (I ſay) ye ſhall ſo cut of the tayle of the ſaid whore of Rome, and (as it were) <hi>her bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch and rush,</hi> that there ſhalbe no more hope left to her lovers heere amongſt vs, of ever committing the like ſpirituall fornication with her heerafter, that heretofore they haue done: that ſo we may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortably apply the former words of <hi>Moſes</hi> to our ſelues and to our children, touching the Romiſh religion and all the appurtinances therof, which we haue ſeene, <hi>that we shall never ſee them againe Exod</hi> 14 23</p>
            <p>Yea let the late conſpiracie of the papiſts before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, provoke you ſo much the more carefully, &amp; firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to aboliſh their whole religion, to the leaſt hem, of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry garment and Ceremony thereof, as alſo the more ſuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to eſtabliſh the Goſpell with all thinges appertainning
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18169:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>therevnto, and every holy meanes for the beſt ſupporting thereof, by how much more, the curſed fruites thereof, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> proclaimed it and dayly doe proclaime it, to be odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ou and abominable in the ſight of God. Laſtly, though the were then diſapoynted, yet your wiſdome is ſuch, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ope ye neede not be admoniſhed, either not to thinke that they will heereafter be idle, and giue over their occupation, of wicked and treaſonable imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, or not to neglect by all good meanes posſible, to prevent whatſoever nature treacherie &amp; conſpiracie, yet they ſhall in their darknes, further practiſe againſt vs.</p>
            <p n="18">18 To conclude therefore, whilſt ye haue time, and whilſt it is called to day, feare that ye ſhall never hereafter haue the like time and oportunitie that now ye haue; and therefore as <hi>Bathſheba</hi> ſaid to her moſt princely ſonne <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muell, Open thy mouth for the dumme, and in the cauſe of all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of deſtruction, open thy mouth, iudge righteouſly, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, afflicted and the poore,</hi> Pro. 31.8.9. So ſay I, to all them that by their place may any way doe good to the Church of God, and to any afflicted &amp; poore members thereof. Yea as the ſaid <hi>Queine Bathsheba</hi> ſaith before, <hi>giue yee ſtrong drinke, to him that is ready to periſh, and wine vnto them that haue greife of heart, that he may drinke, and forget his povertie, and remember his miſerie no more, Pro.</hi> 31.6.7. So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n all them that are of any authoritie, or in any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of grace and favour, eſpecially this preſent high Court of Parliament, to giue a plentifull boll of the ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ke of theire comfortable favour, yea an whole flagon full of the wine of their grace, that they that are now poore, and haue been long heavie hearted for the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; ruins of <hi>Syon,</hi> and that in the greif of their hearts are readie to periſh, may drinke ſo deeplie therof, <hi>that they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18169:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>may forget their povertie, and remember their miſery no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Iob ſaid, that <hi>he had not contemned the iudgment of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, neither of his mayd, when they contended with him.</hi> Iob. 31.13. How much leſſe then is the iudgment of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpell, yea, of the mother of vs all (the Church of God) yea, of God himſelfe, of Chriſt Ieſus, of the holy Angels, of our ſelues and our poſteritie, and final lie of King and kingdome (as hath been ſheewed) to be neglected? As <hi>Haman</hi> ſaid of the Iewes <hi>to Ahashuerosh, that they were a people ſcattered and diſperſed amonge the people in all provinces of his kingdome, having lawes divers from all people, and not obſerving the Kings lawes, and that therefore it was not for the Kings profite to ſuffer them.</hi> Eſter. 3.8. So I am not Ignorant that theſe miniſters of the Goſpell, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue now in theſe Arguments made ſo often mention, are charged as enimyes to the ſtate, perturbers of the Church, ſeditious, ſchiſmaticall etc.</p>
            <p>But if it were lawfull and free for theſe men to expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulate with the ſtate touching the former matters, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> did with the Lords annoyntrd <hi>Saule,</hi> they might not only ſay with <hi>David, wherefore doe ye giue eare to mens words, that ſay, behould</hi> David <hi>ſeeketh evill againſt you?</hi> 1 Sam. 24.10 But they might alſo plead their innocency, as <hi>Dauid</hi> doth his verſe 12, <hi>Vnderſtand and ſee that ther is neither evill, nor wickednes in us, neither haue we ſinned againſt you.</hi> But in the meane time, this they may boldly ſay, that as the former hath been an old accuſation in all ages, even againſt the beſt frends of the Church and ſtate, ſo it is anſwered by the <hi>D. King</hi> in his 42. lecture upon <hi>Ionas</hi> pag 171. out of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> that ſuch accuſations are rather by <hi>conſiction the by conviction.</hi> And therefore as our moſt gratious <hi>Queene</hi> of moſt happie memory <hi>Queene Elizabeth,</hi> before ſhe was
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18169:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>Queene, in her diſtreſſ, in the dayes of <hi>Queene Mary,</hi> wrot with her Diamond in a glaſſe windowe at woodſtoocke,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Much ſuſpected by me,</l>
               <l>Nothing proved can be.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Even ſo may theſe men both ſpeake and write, the ſame of themſelues.</p>
            <p>As for ſuch accuſers as are alwayes provoking all men, eſpecially Princes, and Nobles againſt them, I wiſh them to take heed of that fearefull curſſe, wherwith <hi>David, cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thoſe children of men before the Lord, that had ſturred vp</hi> Saule <hi>againſt him, and that by that meanes had caſt him out from abiding in the inheritance of the Lord, ſaying goe ſerue other Gods,</hi> 1 Sam. 26.19. For my part I pray, that God may giue them a better minde, that ſo they may rather be the bleſſed of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Touching other alſo that haue been or are forward, in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencing, depriving, or otherwiſe moleſting of miniſters, for omisſion of Ceremonies, not obſerving the booke of Common prayer in that ſtrict manner that they doe vrge the ſame, and for other conformitie, (though in other things they doe and cannot but iuſtifie them) I am ſo farr from wiſhyng the leaſt evill unto them, that I doe hartely praye the Lord (who hath the hearts of all in his handes) to worke ſuch a gratious change in them, that they may by all meanes as much further the worke of God, as by their former dealing they haue hindred the ſame. That ſo they may haue all true honor in this life, and be eternal ly bleſſed in the life to come. Finally concernyng our moſt gracious Soveraigne, I haue prayed, I doe praye, and whileſt I liue I will praye for him, as <hi>Salomon</hi> prayed for himſelfe, 1 Kings 2.45. <hi>Let King Iames be bleſſed, and let his throne be ſtabliſhed before the Lord forever:</hi> yea, ſo I pray the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18169:20"/>Lord to bleſſe him, with our Noble <hi>Queene</hi> and all their Royall iſſue, that their earthly kingdome being ended, they may haue the heavenly, and there raigne with Chriſt Ieſus, the King of Kings for ever, and ever. To this prayer, <hi>let all the people ſay</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
